Benjamin Franklin Papers Part 4 -- Letters to Franklin 1779 January-November Mss.B.F85inventory04
American Philosophical Society
- Letters to Benjamin Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 March 30; A.L.S. 2p.; Gérard, Marie-Nicole Grossart de Virly. Versailles
    Reminding Franklin of his promise to take the necessary steps to redeem a snuff-box which she sent to M. [Conrad Alexandre] Gérard [de Rayneval].
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 March 30; A.L.S. 2p.; Hartley, David. London
    Has been much displeased over the delay in the exchange of prisoners; remonstrances he has made; note just received from the Admiralty announcing the sailing of the "Milford" cartel ship for France. Aware that Franklin and he are at one in their desire for peace.
    Printed in Hale's Franklin in France, I, 214.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 March 30; A.L.S. 1p.; Marat, Jean Paul (The Representative of author)
    The Commissioners will hold a meeting on Thursday, Friday or Saturday. Asks Franklin to say which day will be most convenient for him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 March 30; A.L.S. 2p.; Lee, William. Paris
    Repeats request for articles of war for the State of Virginia.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 March 31; A.L.S. 1p.; Bannerman, Benjamin. Roanne
    Had the happiness of knowing Franklin seven years before in America; obliged to take passage for London to settle a small estate of his brother; captured on the way over and carried before the Judge of the Admiralty at Havre-de-Grace, who detained all his possessions and destroyed or lost bonds amounting to a considerable sum; has laid his case before M. de Sartine; hopes to see Franklin at paris; begs that the enclosed letter may be forwarded to Mr. Patrick Henry, Governor of Virginia.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 March 31; A.L.S. 3p.; Adams, John. Brest
    Efforts of M. [Bérube de] Costentin and Captain Landais to save expenses; difficulties on board the "Alliance"; everybody discontented except the captain; intercedes with Franklin to obtain a certain grant of clothing for the petty officers on board and a small sum of money for all the men; his reasons for making this request. Desires Franklin's orders that he may receive a passage on the ship and the necessary sea-stores. Lack of seamen on board the "Alliance"; chance of recruiting them when the American prisoners arrive in England; hopes all these men will not be given to Captain Jones.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 March 31; A.L.S. 1p.; Lee, William
    List of articles wanted by the State of Virginia.
  - to ----- -----, [1778 before July 1]; A.L. 3p.; Grand, Ferdinand
    Comparing England and America. Question of a loan for the United States.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 February 17; A.L.S. 1p.; Le Roy, Jean Baptiste
    Will be at Franklin's house with M. D'Arcy on Friday morning; sorry he did not keep his promise yesterday; Mme. de Maillebois complained of his absence. Experiments with the igneous fluid postponed until he is present.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1779 March 26]; A.L.S. 3p; Le Roy, Jean Baptiste
    Was glad to learn that he was rid of the gout and had at last gone to Versailles, Thinks he will not object now to receive a deputation from the Academy. If weather continues fine can have the experiments to-morrow with the igneous fluid. M. de Maillebois will be there and wishes to see him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1779? March 3]; A.L. 1p.; Le Roy, Jean Baptiste
    Hopes that his latest attack of gout is now relieved. If weather is fine to-morrow "the unknown or anonymous person" will make experiments on the fire principle ("feu principe") at the residence of the Marquis de l'Aubespine.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 April 1; L.S. 2p.; Windship, Amos. Brest
    Concerning his expenses to and from Paris, by direction of P[ierre] Landais.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 April 1; A.L.S. 4p.; Brault and Demezaudré. Saint Malo
    Ambition to establish a house in America; anxious to obtain a passage on board the "Alliance" together with the goods necessary to their establishment; only waiting for Franklin's permission.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 April 1; A.L. in 3d P. 1p.; Mahuet, Catherine-Gabrielle de Rennel, baronne de. Paris
    Wishes to send a letter, by safe conveyance, to Salem, and would be delighted to hear some news of a relative of hers in America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 April 1; A.L.S. 1p; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Report that the cartel, with the American prisoners on board, has arrived in the river. News from Paris of the French successes in the West Indies and the American successes in Georgia.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 April 2; A.L.S. 2p.; Antonio Francesco Salucci et fils. Leghorn
    Desire the earliest news of the expedition they sent to America. Enclose important letter to be sent to America in Franklin's next packet.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 April 2; A.L.S. 2p.; Hartley, David. London
    His continued hopes for peace and his willingness to devote his time and attention to that end. Fears that Europe may be plunged into a general war; America might think the assistance of France dearly bought at such a price.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 April 2; A.L.S. 3p.; Lee, William. Paris
    Complaint of D'Acosta and Co. that the arms, ordered for the State of Virginia by himself and his brother, were refused because they were not furnished at the time agreed upon; reasons for their action.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 April 3; A.L.S. 3p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Understands that Sir J[oseph] Y[orke] has presented a memoir from the English Court, declaring that, in spite of the convoys, England will seize all vessels laden with timber. Thinks M. de N[eufvile] will succeed in his project if given the requisite time; the considerable loan raised by the Empress likely to retard the affair. His opinion of Mr.[William] Lee's presence in Teschen.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 April 3; A.L.S. 3p.; Vernon, William. Boston
    Duplicate of XLV, 204c. Incloses a letter from Governor Greene; visited his seat at Warwick where he had the pleasure of seeing Mrs. Mecom.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 April 3; A.L.S. 1p.; D'Acosta frères. Paris
    Concerning the arms furnished by them on Mr. Lee's order which he refused to receive.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 April 3; L.S. 2p.; Boyd, Lawrence. Brest Road
    Concerning five English prisoners on board the "Patience" brig, who hearing of the cartel for the Americans being settled, have applied to him for a passage to England; begs Franklin to take their case into consideration and grant their discharge.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 April 4; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Tardy, Louis. Paris
    Desires the address in town of the purser of the ship "Alliance."
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 April 4; A.L.S. 2p.; Longwell, James. Calais Prison
    Begs Franklin to procure the release of himself and two other Americans in prison, at Calais; details his misfortunes since leaving America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 April 4; A.L.S. 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Introducing Mr. Wilkinson, the ingenious director and projector of a very fine foundry on the Loire; Dr. Priestley's wife is a sister of Mr. Wilkinson.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 April 5; L.S. 2p.; Richardson, Mary. Plymouth
    Is the sixteen-year-old daughter of Anthony Richardson, merchant, who was drowned or murdered in New York. Came over to England with her blind mother who wishes to consult a famous oculist; their vessel shipwrecked and all their belongings lost. Anxious to return to America and begs Franklin's assistance.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 April 5; A.L.S. 3p.; Philantropos
    Fears that France may be compelled to withdraw from her alliance with America because of the advantages England has gained over her, and then England's great armaments would be wholly directed against America and greatly distress her. Outlines a general plan of war which should be adopted by France, in case Spain joins her against Great Britain; what France should do if Spain does not join her.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1779] April 25; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Genet, [Edme Jacques]
    Sending Franklin the paper containing the letter to the King.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1780?] April 6; A.L.S. 1p.; Cabanis, Pierre Jean Georges. Auteuil
    Returning Franklin the corrected proof. Constantly thinking of him at Auteuil; remembrances from the Lady of Auteuil [Madame Helvetius] and the Abbé de la Roche.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 April 6; A.L.S. 2p.; Wanklyn. I. Paris
    Is a dissenting minister, a native of America; persecution he underwent in England for defending the American cause from the pulpit; his imprisonment on board an English frigate and his subsequent escape; his arrival in Paris in a destitute condition. Desires Franklin's assistance to enable him to go to America, where he wishes to serve his country either in the pulpit or army.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 April 6; A.L.S. 1p.; Wilkin, David. La Rochelle
    Desires to be released from his imprisonment and enabled to return to Philadelphia where he has a wife and family; Thomas Campbell, also a Philadelphian, desires his freedom.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 April 6; A.L.S. 3p.; Landais, Capt. Pierre. Brest
    Would rather have all Americans in his crew than a part French, as that mixture always causes trouble. Has landed all the mutineers. Concering the arrival of the cartel vessel at Nantes with ninety-seven Americans; his orders to take with him, for exchange, ninety-three prisoners out of the guard-ship; danger of carrying so many, even in irons. Asks Franklin's advice in the case of a deserter from his ship, who has enlisted in Colonel Dillon's regiment and is at present on board a man-of-war, where they refuse to give him up.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 April 7; A.L.S. 2p.; Potter, Thomas. Haver-de-Grace
    Applies as an American for his release from prison, that he may be enabled once more to serve his country.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 April 7; A.L.S. 4p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Arrival in the "Flagg" of ninety-five American prisoners, twelve of whom are officers; proposals made them by the agent; given only 20 sols per day for board; begs for better treatment for the officers; if a subscription is opened for the subsistence of prisoners, will give 20 louis; enclosing a list of men who have engaged in the British service and a list of those who remain in prison; hopes Franklin will not be offended at his taking the part of the prisoners.
  - to Benjamin Franklin., 1779 April 7; A.L.S. 1p.; Longwell, James. Calais Prison
    Has received no answer to his former letters; repeats all he said in XIV, 10.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1779.] April 7; A.L. in 3d P. 1p.; La Rochefoucauld, Louis Alexandre, duc de
    Sends a rough draft of a letter to the Keeper of the Seals.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1779.] April 8; A.L.S. 1p.; Barbeu-Dubourg, -----
    The meeting is for the following day. If Franklin can attend he will go also.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 April 8; A.L.S. 1p.; Amelot de Chaillou, Antoine-Jean. Versailles
    Has just heard the Franklin expects to read a paper at the Academy of Sciences on the 14th inst.; expects the other members, who have papers for that meeting, to dine with him on the 12th and read their memoirs in presence of the officers of the Academy; begs the honor of Franklin's company.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 April 9; A.L.S. 1p.; Auzéville, Gerard d'.
    Desires to buy a few acres in America and devote himself to agriculture; applies to Franklin for the advance of a sufficient sum to do this.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 April 9; A.L.S. 4p.; Boule, -----. Passy
    His persent state of destitution; is almost driven insane; begs for assistance.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 April 9; A.L. 4p.; Vaughan, Benjamin. London
    Concerning the edition of Franklin's writings; the liberties he has allowed himself as editor; his reasons for making certain alterations. Heard from Mr. Galloway that "the rebels" had destroyed some of his and of Franklin's papers; awaits further details. Has taken up Franklin's paper on the Vis inertia to comment upon it.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 April 9; A.L.S. 1p.; Ingenhousz, Jan
    Will bring or send Franklin the copper pot for roasting chickens in, which he bought at Sheffield. Dr. Priestley's new volume on air will contain a letter written by himself on the method of producing, at pleasure, any quantity of inflammable air. Good time to send a ship to discover the North Pole; thinks it probable, owing to the mildness of the weather during the preceding year, that the seas will be free from ice.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 April 9; A.L.S. 3P.; Barbeu-Dubourg, Jacques.
    Recalls to Franklin's memory, the experiments in physics and chemistry performed by M. Brongniart; desires to procure for him the place of demonstrator of chemistry at the Jardin du Roy, vacant by the death of M. [Hilaire Marin] Rouelle; desires Franklin's influence with M. de Buffon, in whose power lies the choice.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 April 10; A.L.S. 3p.; Pollock, Oliver. New Orleans
    Concerning various bills of exchange which he has drawn for the use of the United States to execute the orders he received from Congress, and which he hopes will be duly honored by Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 April 10; A.L.S. 3p.; Lloyd, Richard Bennett. London
    Desires advice on the wisdom of embarking for New York with his wife and children, and then passing to his estate in Maryland.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 April 10; A.L.S. 2p.; Gover, Robert. Saint Valery-sur-Somme
    Is a native of Baltimore, Md.; was shipwrecked on the coast of France, and made prisoner; desires to enter the service of Congress.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 April 10; A.L.S. 2p.; Taylor, Jesse. Belfast
    A considerable number are resolved on the expedition, mentioned in his last of November 21st, including besides himself and family, various genlemen of consideration; their influence, when settled in America, will induce hundreds of their countrymen to follow, who will be glad to leave a kingdom in which they labor under insult and oppression. Eager for Franklin to procure and forward the security so anxioulsy solicited; extreme secrecy to be observed prevents their sending the required descriptive list.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 April 10; A.L.S. 2p.; Wagener, Philip. Rotterdam
    Is impecunious and in a strange country. Asks money to go to America, there being an American ship in port. Promises to refund loan on arrival in America.
    (See LIX, 3.)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 April 11.; A.L.S. 1p.; Hutton, James
    Sends for that promised protection for the "Good Intent," Captain Francis Mugford, which goes to and from Labrador to the Moravian Mission Settlements for the conversion of the heathen.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 April 12; Kéralio, Agathon Guynement, chevalier de
    Madame la Comtesse de Forbach sends the enclosed letter to Franklin and begs him to read the memoir in favor of M. le Baron de Ried, and send a short reply that she may prove her commission accomplished.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 April 12; A.L.S. 2p.; Marat, Jean Paul (The Representative of author)
    Requesting Dr. Franklin's presence at the meeting of the Committee and that he give his opinion of certain discoveries which would influence public opinion, and his sanction would silence a hostile cabal.
    Printed in Works (Smyth, VII, 286).
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 April 13; A.L.S. 4p.; Sayre, Stephen. Copenhagen
    Has been ill many days. Had an audience with the King of Sweden, à propos of the advisability of Sweden getting possession of Porto Rico or some island in the West Indies, for purposes of trade, etc.; is everywhere taken to be in the employ of Congress; has neither abused the character nor assumed it. Desires letters to the Governor of Dominica whither he expects to go to secure an estate he owns there. Begs Franklin to mention him once more to Congress.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 April 13; A.L.S. 3p.; John, Adams. Nantes
    Glad that he approves of clothing the petty officers and will do his best to justify the confidence placed in him. The lack of obedience and discipline on board must cause delays of all kinds. Much pleased at Franklin's flattering reception at Court; hopes that Spain, as well as France, will soon declare in favor of the same generous cause. England's fondness for war, and obstinacy in carrying it on. Master Johnny acts as interpreter, companion, secretary and domestic to his papa.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 April 13; A.L.S. 2p.; Adams, John. Nantes
    The reason for the discontent on board seems to be the depreciation of paper pay and the nationality of the captain (Landais). Has promised the officers and men as much money as, with their clothes, will make two months' pay: without this indulgence, in convinced the ship would never get to sea.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 April 13; A.L.S. 2p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    His difficulties in procuring a trial. His opinion of falling in love and marriage; sees more reasons in favor of matrimony than he used to in the past.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1779 April 14; A.L.S. 3p.; Jay, Sir James. Paris
    Asks for reason for his exclusion from taking passage on the vessel with M. Gérard and Mr. Deane.
    A.E. by Franklin. "Being sure that there has been no intention nor inclination to offend Sir James Jay, and not being conscious of having done or said anything that ought to give offense, his note is perfectly unintelligible to the gentleman it is directed to."
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 April 14; A.L.S. 2p.; Hutton, James
    Thanking him for the kind paper of protection for their vessel; has sent it to England to his brethren; hopes for the same kind of passport from M. de Sartine. Difficulties attending the release of Captain Mugford, the mate and two sailors, which must be accomplished before they can sail.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 April 14; L. 2p.; Duchemin, Daniel. London
    Was first-lieutenant in Colonel Armand's troop in the service of America; was made prisoner in Philadelphia two days before the entry of the English; through friends, obtained a passage to England, which country he is unable to leave, owing to lack of funds; desires Franklin's assistance.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 April 14; A.L.S. 2p.; Hutton, James
    Concerning the exchange of four prisoners, in whom he is very much interested. Desires the passport as soon as it can be procured from the French.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 April 15; A.L.S. 1p.; Hutton, James
    Obtained, from M. de Sartine, the desired passport. Proud of the praise given to Franklin's paper on the Aurora Borealis, read before the Academy of Sciences.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, VIII, 325).
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 April 16; A.L.S. 1p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Sending him Sir J[oseph] Y[orke]'s memoir mentioned in his letter of the 13th.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 April 16; A.L.S. 1p.; Pierel, J. Roscoff
    Announcing the arrival of an English prize in their port, taken by Captain Nathaniel West, of the " Black Prince," from Salem, N.H.; the sale will take place at once. Will continue to aid American captains to the best of his abilities.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 April 16; A.L.S. 2p.; Connor, John. Dinan Castle
    On his way to Bordeaux, in an American merchantman, was taken prisoner by an English sloop-of-war and carried to England; on his release, being destitute, was obliged to enlist on board an English privateer, which was later captured by the French; ever since that time has been confined in the above prison; begs Franklin to procure his release that he may return to his wife and children in Norfolk, Va.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 April 16; L.S. 2p.; Woestyn frères. Dunkirk
    Extremely anxious that Franklin should permit them to name thier frigate after him; the influence such a name would have in promoting thier enterprise, in which they would consider themselves only too fortunate, should Franklin take an interest.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 [?] April 17; A.L.S. 1p.; Barbeu-Dubourg, Jacques. Paris
    Recommends the enclosed letter to Franklin's care, written by a devoted mother, a friend of Mlle. Basseport, to her son in Philadelphia.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 April 17; L. 2p.; ----, ----
    Regarding the capture of indigo by Captain Davison, who held no commission from Congress, from a ship commanded by Captain Noble, from New York for London, and carried into a Swedish port.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 April 17; A.L.S. 2p.; Emery, Jno. Bilbao
    Concerning the cutter "Saucy Jack," Captain Sargent Ingersoll, which was taken too nigh the shore to be a legal prize; the cutter belongs to himself and Nat[haniel] Tracy, of Newburyport; begs Franklin to mention the affair to Count d'Aranda on the chance that she may be recovered.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 April 17; A.L.S. 2p.; MacCreery, William. Bordeaux
    Answers Franklin's inquiries concerning the duties on the exportation of salt from ports of France. Expects to sail in the Buckskin about the 10th of May, if Franklin has any letters or despatches he desires to send.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 April 17; L in 3d P. 1p.; Amchaga, M. d'
    Making an appointment to see Franklin the next day; hopes to see him Monday at M. Amelot's dinner.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 April 17; A.L.S. 2p.; Lavalette, -----
    Desires to serve in the American army; his parents' former opposition, for the present removed; will send Franklin the necessary certificates of his services in the French army.
    A.E. by Franklin. Thanks! The American army is full.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 April 17; A.L.S. 1p.; Joseph Gardoqui and Sons. Bilbao
    Forwards the enclosed letter and asks Franklin's kind assistance to help recover Mr. Emery's s interest.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 April 17; A.L.S. 5p.; Bondfield, John. Bordeaux
    Enclosing a list of the mercantile operations wherein he has embarked; the disagreeable situation he finds himself in, owing to the general discredit caused by the failure of many houses, particularly those connected with America. In order to provide against a possible storm, applies to Franklin for credit, if it can be done without prejudice to his Ministry; goes into details.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 April 19; A.L.S. 2p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    The French Ambassador angry at not receiving his confidence in the affair between Messrs. St[urle]r, de N[eufville] and himself; has not shown him Franklin's last four letters; his accusations against Mr. Sturler; desires Franklin's advice in the matter.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 April 19; L.S. 2p.; Steward, John et al. St Malo
    Four American seamen in prison appeal for their release and to be allowed to serve under Captain Jones or on the "Reliance" ["Alliance"].
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 April 19; A.L.S. 1p.; Landais, Capt. Pierre. Nantes
    Giving an account of his proceedings since leaving Brest on the 11th; is waiting to deliver his ninety-three English prisoners to the English cartel ship, according to Mr. Schweighauser's orders.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 April 20; A.L.S. 2p.; Francalanza, Félicie Françoise. Lisbon
    Reasons for believing that she is a relative of Franklin; narrates her family history; obliged to practice the strictest economy, since the loss of her fortune; begs Franklin's assistance.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 April 20; A.L.S. 3p.; Becker and Saltzmann. Berlin
    Have about four thousand uniforms left, after supplying the German soldiers; offers these to Franklin for the Americans at a greatly reduced rate.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 April 20; A.L.S. 1p.; Willams, Jonathan Jr. Nantes